<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry id='mixal1'>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>MIXAL</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class='date'>18 May 2003</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='source'>Retrocomputing Museum</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='manual'>Mixal user's manual</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv id='name'>
<refname>mixal</refname>
<refpurpose>a load-and-go MIX assembler</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refsynopsisdiv id='synopsis'>
<cmdsynopsis>
  <command>mixal</command>    
    <arg choice='opt' rep='repeat'><replaceable>file</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1 id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<para><application>mixal</application> is an implementation of the
hypothetical <acronym>MIX</acronym> computer and its assembly language
called <acronym>MIXAL</acronym>.  The computer was designed by Donald
Knuth for use in his monumental and yet to be finished book series
<citetitle>The Art of Computer Programming</citetitle>.  All programs
and all programming exercises in the book are written in the
<acronym>MIXAL</acronym> language.</para>

<para>This implementation is a load-and-go assembler, meaning that you
provide it with a <acronym>MIXAL</acronym> program source, which it
translates into <acronym>MIX</acronym> machine code, which it promptly
executes by acting as a <acronym>MIX</acronym> emulator.</para>

<para>You give <application>mixal</application> zero or more
<acronym>MIXAL</acronym> program source files in the command line,
which the program interprets.  If you give it no arguments, it expects
to find a program in the standard input stream.  After the program has
executed, the final state of the machine registers is printed to the
standard output stream.</para>

<para>The card punch and line printer devices are connected to the standard
input and output stream, respectively.  Console input and output are
connected to standard input and output, and the disk devices are
connected to files named diskN in the current directory, where N is
the device number.  Those files are created on demand.</para>

<para>There is one significant difference between the MIXAL input
language and MIX as originally described by Knuth: Knuth puts fields
at fixed offsets on a line, while this implementation expects them to
be separated by whitespace.  (Purists may wish to fix this obvious
bug.)  Since the ALF directive, which defines constant strings,
becomes ambiguous when delimited by whitespace, there's a new syntax
to achieve the same effect. Instead of

<programlisting>
	ALF	 rime
</programlisting>

use

<programlisting>
	CON	" rime"
</programlisting>
</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='bugs'><title>BUGS</title>
<para>This <acronym>MIXAL</acronym> implementation does not do
floating-point.  The tape devices are not implemented.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='author'><title>AUTHOR</title>
<para>This <acronym>MIXAL</acronym> implementation was designed and
written by Darius Bacon, and then ported to Unixish systems and
debugged by Eric S. Raymond.  This version includes corrections to
multiplication and division by Larry Gately.  This manual page was
written for Debian by Antti-Juhani Kaijanaho, with changes by Darius
Bacon and Eric S. Raymond.</para>

<para>The MIXAL language was designed by Donald Knuth.  We gratefully
acknowledge the general permission granted by Dr. Knuth and Addison-Wesley to
redistribute MIX documentation and examples from <citetitle>The Art of
Computer Programming</citetitle> in connection with open-source
implementations of the language and under the license terms of those
implementations.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id='see_also'><title>SEE ALSO</title>
<para>The files <filename>/usr/share/doc/mixal/README</filename> and
<filename>/usr/share/doc/mixal/NOTES</filename> contain some
information about this <acronym>MIXAL</acronym> implementation.</para>

<para>A description of the <acronym>MIX</acronym> system and the
<acronym>MIXAL</acronym> language can be found in Donald E. Knuth's
book <citetitle>The Art of Computer Programming</citetitle>, Volume 1:
<citetitle>Fundamental Algorithms</citetitle>; 3rd Edition
(Addison-Wesley 1997).  (Or see the home page at <ulink
url='http://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~knuth/taocp.html'>http://www-cs-faculty.stanford.edu/~knuth/taocp.html</ulink>.)</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

